<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Python on Koorosh's Website</title><link>https://kooroshmoslemi.github.io/categories/python/</link><description>Recent content in Python on Koorosh's Website</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://kooroshmoslemi.github.io/categories/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Designing an ETL Pipeline for a Data Warehouse</title><link>https://kooroshmoslemi.github.io/posts/etl-pipeline/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://kooroshmoslemi.github.io/posts/etl-pipeline/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This project was my final submission for a database course instructed by &lt;a href="https://scholar.google.ca/citations?user=7Eng5oAAAAAJ&amp;amp;hl=en" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Dr. Gheibi&lt;/a&gt;. The project was divided into three main phases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database Design&lt;/strong&gt;: The first phase required designing a database for a library, ensuring it adhered to the fifth normal form (5NF).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ETL Pipeline&lt;/strong&gt;: The second phase involved creating an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extract,_transform,_load" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;ETL (Extract, Transform, Load)&lt;/a&gt; pipeline to synchronize a data warehouse with the operational database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Machine&lt;/strong&gt;: The final phase was to develop a &amp;ldquo;time machine&amp;rdquo; feature that could restore the database to a specific point in the past.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the ETL pipeline, a common approach is to replicate each database operation individually, but this can create significant overhead. Instead, I modeled the database as a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Directed_acyclic_graph" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Directed Acyclic Graph (DAG)&lt;/a&gt;, where tables and their relationships were represented as vertices and edges. I then used a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Topological_sorting" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;topological sort&lt;/a&gt; of this DAG to determine the optimal order for applying bulk insert, delete, and update operations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>